All right. Michael was talking about צום גדליה Tzom Gedalia beforehand. All
right, so today's דף daf is ח, ches, but we are picking
up on the top of ז עמוד ב. zayin amud bais. We
are about six lines from the top, and we had been discussing
whether when you take the מנחה mincha from the כלי kli or
put the קומץ komets into a כלי, kli, so it requires a
כלי שרת, klishareis, do you—does the record—can it be on the ground
or do you need a כהן kohein to hold it? So we
said based on the שולחן, shulchan, which was quite a fascinating comparison
because even if you consider the bread on the שולחן shulchan like
a מנחה, mincha, which the גמרא gemara does, but nevertheless, that's a
כלי kli that's made to be on the ground. But the גמרא
gemara says based on the שולחן, shulchan, you see that כלי kli
can be on the ground. But now we are going to say
there is one aspect that we have not explored. So let's take
a look. Again, ז עמוד ב, zayin amud bais, six lines from
the top, middle of the line, אמר רבא. amar rava. So Rava
says, פשיטא לי, peshita li, it's obvious to me, קומץ מכלי שעל
גבי קרקע. komets mikli she'al gabei karka. You can take the קמיצה
kmeetsa if the כלי שרת, klishareis, if the vessel is on the
ground. How do you know that? שכן מצינו בסילוק בזיכין. shekein matzinu
bisiluk bazeichin. Because when you remove the little spoons of incense from
the שולחן, shulchan, those are the קומץ. komets. Those correspond to the
קומץ komets for, you know, for the מנחה. mincha. If you look
at the whole bread on the שולחן shulchan as a מנחה. mincha.
So the twelve loaves are the remainder which gets eaten, and the
קומץ komets which gets burnt is these little spoons of incense. And
even though there's no flour in there. And even though there's no
flour, but conceptually that's the role that they fill, how they function.
So therefore, since you take the בזיכין bazeichin from the table, you
see you can take the קומץ komets from a vessel that's on
the ground. מקדשין מנחה בכלי שעל גבי קרקע, mekadshin mincha bikli she'al
gabei karka,
and you can originally put the מנחה mincha into a vessel that's
on the ground, although that requires קידוש כלי. kidush keli. Why? שכן
מצינו בסידור בזיכין. shekein matzinu bisidur bazeichin.
Because that's what happens when you basically put the not only בזיכין,
bazeichin, but when you put the loaves with the spoons on the
table. That's like the sanctifying of the מנחה, mincha, the original putting
it in the כלי, kli, and there the כלי, kli, the table,
is on the ground. So we have that you put it on
the כלי kli on the ground, you take it from the כלי
kli on the ground, but we're missing one step. What happens after
you take the קומץ? komets? You then put it in another one.
Put the קומץ komets into another כלי. kli. So does that final
כלי, kli, can that be on the ground? And here there's a
good logic to say not, I mean even bracketing the weirdness of
the שולחן shulchan analogy. Because from the moment you take the קומץ,
komets, you're really starting the process, I mean, of the עבודה avoda
and the bringing of the קומץ komets to the מזבח. mizbeiyach. It's
true there's something that precedes the קומץ. komets. The כהן kohein takes
the מנחה mincha and touches the corner of the מזבח, mizbeiyach, that's
in the פסוק. pasuk. But nevertheless, you know, קמיצה kmeetsa is really
that's where פיגול pigul starts to matter, that's where you're starting to
take the קמיצה kmeetsa and to bring it up to the מזבח.
mizbeiyach. So there you can understand that you need the כהנים kohanim
to be involved in that process and it had to be sort
of like an active process. When you put it on the ground,
you're sort of stopping the process. It's no longer sort of—it's no
longer in the process of being brought to the מזבח. mizbeiyach. So
you can understand why that stage would require a כהן. kohein.
I understand, but I'm saying it's not, you know, you can understand
that now actually talking about getting the כהנים kohanim involved and being
more active and therefore you really do need it to be held.
So that's Rava's question. בעי רבא קידוש קומץ מאי? bai rava kidush
komets mai? What's the story about the קידוש קומץ? kidush komets? ממנחה
ילפינן לה? mimincha yafinan lah? Do we learn it out from the
מנחה mincha itself from earlier stages where we said the original placing
in and taking out does—the כלי kli can be on the ground?
או מדם ילפינן לה? o midam yafinan lah? Or do we say,
no, no, no, let's now compare it to other, you know, analogies
to other קרבנות korbanot how they work starting with this process. So
stuff that happens in the מנחה mincha to sanctify it in a
vessel, taking it from the vessel, there's no analog to the קרבן,
korban, to the animal sacrifice. But from the time you do the
קמיצה, kmeetsa, right, so I mean there the כלי kli aspect there's
no analog, but from that point on there is an analog because
you put it in a כלי kli like the דם dam is
caught in a כלי, kli, and then you bring it to the
מזבח mizbeiyach and then you offer it up on the מזבח. mizbeiyach.
So maybe starting from that point we should start looking at the
analogs of the animal sacrifices. And there we assume that not, you
know, we don't only assume, we say very clearly the כלי kli
cannot be on the ground. Why? Why?
Because what is one of the עבודות? avodos? The first עבודה avoda
by the animal is שחיטה. shechita. What's the next עבודה? avoda? Well,
we have קבלת הדם. kabalas hadam. So it's an act of קבלת
הדם. kabalas hadam. Now here's actually an interesting difference, right? Why do
you need the כלי kli to be held by a כהן kohein
for the דם? dam? Because one of the עבודות avodos is defined
as an act of קבלת הדם. kabalas hadam. You don't have an
act if the כלי kli is on the ground. But by a
מנחה, mincha, right, the act is, you know, it's not like you're
just the act is catching, the act is pitching, more or less,
you know. The act is you're placing the קטורת ktoreis into the
כלי, kli, so you can have the act without the כלי kli
being held. So that's the question. Now we're in a realm where
we start looking at the analogs of the animal sacrifices,
but מנחה mincha is still going to be
different just— But what do they mean by holding it? I mean,
you can still hold it on the ground, right? In other words,
because like you have the ממרס, memares, right? The כלי kli is
still on the ground, isn't it? You know, that's an... okay, ממרס
memares is an interesting proof because ממרס memares was not that stage.
No, I know, but it's still... that's an interesting question. If you
held it and it was touching the ground, is the problem that
it's touching the ground or the problem that there's... it's not being
held by a כהן? kohen? My assumption is the problem is it's
not being held by a כהן, kohen, but I don't know. I
have not seen a discussion about that. Okay, so let's take a
look at the... what? Oh, it looks like
the camera's centered. Okay, so let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara
says מדמיא... midamya... הדר... hadar... בעי רבא, ba'ya Rava, blah blah blah.
הדר פשט. hadar pashat.
Then he finally came to a conclusion: מדמיא ילפינן. midamya yalfinan. Now,
it's quite interesting when you have that, you know, בעי והדר פשט,
ba'ya vehadar pashat, because it doesn't tell you what his reasoning was
and it certainly doesn't seem like he had textual evidence. It just
seems like logically he said, okay, at this stage we're starting to
look at the analogs by animal sacrifices, and you need somebody holding
the כלי kli the same way you do by the blood. So
you need two כהנים kohanim then. So you need two כהנים kohanim
at that stage, right. Because you can't put it in your other
hand. Right, because you need to use your right hand. Okay. ומי
אמר רבא הכי? U'mi amar Rava hachi? Did רבא Rava really say
that? ואיתמר, Ve'itmar, it was taught: קומץ שחלקו בשני כלים. kometz she-chalako
b'shnei keilim.
Let's say you divided the קומץ kometz into two vessels. You didn't
put it... after you took it, you didn't put the whole thing
in one vessel, you put half in one and half in the
other. Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha? Where are we? חלקו בשני
כלים. chalako b'shnei keilim. רב נחמן אמר אינו קדוש. Rav Nachman amar
eino kadosh. It's not holy. ורבא אמר קדוש. Ve-Rava amar kadosh. It
is holy. Now, where would we have an idea that you need
to put it all in one vessel? So we are going to
see that we get this idea from the הזאה haza'ah by the
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, and that's basically it goes a couple stages.
From the הזאה haza'ah of פרה אדומה parah adumah we learn to
the קבלה kabbalah of the blood of a קרבן, korban, that it
all has to be caught... or not all, but the entire amount
you need, the כדי הזאה k'dei haza'ah has to be caught in
one vessel. Okay, so we know that the entire amount has to
be caught. But רבא Rava is saying by a מנחה mincha you
don't have to put it all in one vessel, you can put
it in two vessels. And it's actually the exact same stage. It's
the stage of putting the קומץ kometz in the כלי, kli, catching
the blood in the vessel. And whereas by the blood, it all
has to be in... you have to get a full amount in
a vessel, by מנחה mincha you don't need a full amount in
a vessel. You can have it in two vessels. So רבא Rava
is not learning strictly from the blood. That's the גמרא's Gemara question.
So let's take a look again. והא
איתמר קומץ שחלקו בשני כלים. Ve-ha itmar kometz she-chalako b'shnei keilim. You
divide it into vessels. רב נחמן אמר אינו קדוש. Rav Nachman amar
eino kadosh. It's not holy. ורבא אמר קדוש. Ve-Rava amar kadosh. It
is קדוש. kadosh. ואי איתא, Ve-im itha, if רבא Rava really learns
from the blood and the putting... catching of the blood in the
vessel, ליליף מדמיא? laleif midamya? Let him learn from blood that, as
we're about to say, blood... the full amount that you need has
to be caught in one vessel, and so how can a מנחה
mincha be good in two? So he's saying maybe you did get
the full amount that you need in one vessel and then there's
more? No, no, no. Then they wouldn't be debating. The debate of
two vessels is that initial act of placing it... of placing it.
Okay,
and the קומץ kometz is only the size of a קומץ. kometz.
It's only the... you know, that's the minimum and the maximum is
a קומץ. kometz. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says: הדר ביה
רבא מההיא. hadar beih Rava me-hahi. All right, רבא Rava reversed himself.
Now, the question always is which one did he reverse himself from?
רש"י Rashi says here... where's רש"י? Rashi? מההיא דודאי אינו קדוש
דמדמיא ילפינן. me-hahi de-vada'i eino kadosh de-midamya yalfinan. That
the גמרא Gemara is very much following the first approach that רבא
Rava learns from the blood scenario and therefore he would in the
end agree that you have to put the entire קמיצה kmitzah in
one vessel, the same way the minimum amount of blood has to
be caught in one vessel. You got it? Okay. So, הדר ביה
רבא מההיא. hadar beih Rava me-hahi. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
now we're going to look at this debate or at the... why
we take for granted that the minimum amount of blood has to
be caught in one vessel. So let's take a look.
I'm sorry, I keep on losing my place. Okay, הדר ביה רבא
מההיא. hadar beih Rava me-hahi. ודם מנלן דלא קדוש חציין? Ve-dam minalan
d'lo kadosh chatziyan?
Where do we know that blood is not sanctified if the minimum
amount is caught in two vessels? Obviously, there's tons of blood so
you don't even have to catch all of it, לכתחילה l'chatchila you
do but בדיעבד b'diavad you don't. But if the minimum amount is
divided between two vessels... דתני רב תחליפא בר שמואל. dtani Rav Tachlipa
bar Shmuel.
We're at the line about a third of the way down that
begins with a ה heh in brackets. So רב תחליפא בר שמואל
Rav Tachlipa bar Shmuel taught a ברייתא: braitah: קידש פחות מכדי הזאה
בכלי זה. kideish pachot mikdei haza'ah b'kli zeh.
So we're going to start actually by the sprinkling of the פרה
אדומה. parah adumah. Now, there is a minimum amount that you need
to do a הזאה. haza'ah. You have to have enough liquid that
it can be sort of absorbed by the hyssop that you're dipping
in and then sprinkle. So whatever that is amount... I mean it's
a tiny amount, but there's still an amount. There's less than that
it won't work. So let's say when you put the... you know,
put the ashes in, which is called the... sanctifying of it, you
put less than the minimum amount in one vessel and less than
the minimum amount in another vessel. Can you now combine them and
do the הזיה hazah or is that not considered an act of
sanctifying because you never had as the entire minimum amount together when
you did the sanctifying? So that's the issue. Okay. And the answer
is it's not. You need the entire minimum amount together. Okay. קידש
פחות מכדי הזאה בכלי זה, kidesh pachos mikdei hazah bichli zeh,
you sanctified less than the amount of sprinkling in one vessel, ופחות
מכדי הזאה בכלי זה, upachos mikdei hazah bichli zeh, and less than
the minimum amount in another vessel, לא קידש, lo kidash, you did
not sanctify the water of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah and you
cannot use it for sprinkling even if you combine it after. So
that we know by פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, we're going to say
in a minute where we learned that from. איבעיא להו, ibay'u lehu,
and we raise the question, בדם מאי, b'dam mai, what is the
story by the blood of a קרבן? korban? Is it the same
הלכה? halacha? הלכתא היא, hilchasa hi, is this a law passed down
from משה מסיני? Moshe miSinai? It's not based on a פסוק pasuk
and it's the special technical arbitrary law by פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah,
cannot be extrapolated. ומהלכתא לא ילפינן, umaihilchasa lo yalfinan, from these technical
details essentially we would not extrapolate. או דילמא, o dilma, no, maybe
it's based on a פסוק. pasuk. התם מאי טעמא, hasam mai ta'ama,
what's the reason that you and what's the reason that we learn
out that you need a minimum amount by the sprinkling? דכתיב וטבל
במים, dichsiv v'taval bamayim, you should dip in the water. The בה
ba is בהא, b'ha, the water. So חז"ל Chazal learned from the
the part of it that there has to be the necessary amount.
By the way, one of the things, mistake that you make people
go back for in ליינינג laining if you're paying attention is when
they mess up a bi and a ba or a li and
a la, because although that sounds trivial, it's the difference between a
direct object or not, the, a direct object. לי li X means
to, like to place.
לשולחן, lishulchan, לשולחן, lishulchan, to the table.
לשולחן lashulchan means להשולחן, l'hashulchan, to the table. Okay, fine. So anyway,
וטבל במים. v'taval bamayim. הכא נמי הכתיב, hacha nami hacksiv, so that's
why we say you need the minimum amount of water. So by
blood also says וטבל בדם, v'taval badam, in the blood. So we
should say that you should need to have all the minimum amount
of blood in the vessel to be sanctified.
ואיתמר, v'itmar, and then we taught, אמר רב זריקא אמר רבי אלעזר,
amar Rav Zrika amar Rabbi Elazar, אף בדם לא קידש. af badam
lo kidash.
So even by blood it does not become sanctified when it's caught
in the vessel unless you have the minimum amount. Now again notice
that the idea of כלי שרת klei sharet is adding another stage
of קדושה. kedusha. Obviously the מנחה mincha is already קדוש, kadosh, the
blood is already קדוש, kadosh, as opposed to the water of the
פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, it doesn't have any status until the two
are mixed. Nevertheless we say not just that if you caught it
in two vessels it's a פסול קבלת הדם, pasul kabbalas hadam, we
say it's לא קידש, lo kidash, that somehow the effect of the
כלי שרת klei sharet to raise the קדושה kedusha of the blood
to now can be thrown on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the קדושה kedusha
is only effective when you have the minimum amount together. Okay, so
that's true there by the blood, maybe the same is true by
the מנחה mincha that you need the minimum amount to have the
קדושה kedusha of the כלי שרת. klei sharet. All right, so let's
take a look.
אמר רבא תניא נמי הכי, amar Rava tanya nami hacha, so we
taught similarly, וטבל, v'taval, so it says he should dip his finger
in the blood, this is by the כהן, kohen, ולא מספיג, v'lo
maspig, not sopping up, not like when you do like you have
batter from a cake and you run your hand around the rim,
right? So we have this, we have this already, so that's not
good, the liquid has to be sort of collected in the bottom
and you have to dip into the liquid. You're not just collecting
the little droplets that are on the rim. Okay, so that's וטבל
v'taval to dip, we're not talking about Shabbos.
ולא מספיג, v'lo maspig, not like a sopping up, sponging up. בדם,
badam, in the blood, שתהא בדם שיעור טבילה מעיקרו, shete'hei badam shiur
tvilah m'ikaro, that there has to be the minimum amount originally, the
keyword being originally from the moment it was caught. מן הדם, min
hadam, from the blood, מן הדם שבענין, min hadam sheba'inyan, from the
blood we were talking about. Now what does that mean? We'll see
in a minute. Okay, but let's first now focus on the first
two about the
not sponging up and the minimum amount altogether. ואיצטריך למכתב וטבל ואיצטריך
למכתב בדם, v'iztrich limichsav v'taval v'iztrich limichsav badam,
you needed to write both. דאי כתב רחמנא וטבל, de'i kasav rachmana
v'taval, had it just said dip, הוה אמינא hava amina אף על
גב דלא קיבל שיעור טבילה מעיקרו, af al gav d'lo kibel shiur
tvilah m'ikaro,
even if you did not catch the minimum amount originally, meaning I
understand that when I come to dip my finger I need the
minimum amount to be there, okay, but it but maybe I could
catch a little bit in one vessel, little in another, mix it,
and then when I come to dip my finger, then I'll have
the amount that I need to dip. So if it just said
וטבל, v'taval, it would have referred to the act I'm doing now,
that it has to be dipping in collected liquid, not going around
the rim, but it would not have indicated how that liquid got
to the vessel and maybe it got there from two minimum vessels.
Okay, so
there that is what I would have learned from וטבל v'taval but
I wouldn't have known everything. וכתב רחמנא בדם, V'chtav Rachamana badam,
it says in the blood, meaning the blood that was always there,
and there has to have been a minimum amount there. ואי כתב
רחמנא בדם, V'ei chtav Rachamana badam, the blood, הוה אמינא, hava amina,
so then I would have known you need the minimum amount to
begin with, but I wouldn't have known the action of dipping. And
הוה אמינא, hava amina, אפילו מספיג, afilu maspig,
even if you were like sponging it, you know. So וכתב רחמנא
וטבל v'chtav Rachamana v'taval and וכתב רחמנא וטבל. v'chtav Rachamana v'taval. Therefore
it also says וטבל. v'taval. So וטבל v'taval is the act of
dipping in collected liquid, not going around the edge. And בדם badam
is that the entire minimum amount of blood was there from the
beginning. That's how you dip the finger for the דם, dam, and
that's where we know that the minimum amount has to be caught
originally. Now we talk about the last phrase, מן הדם שבענין למעוטי
מאי, min hadam shebe'inyan l'mutei mai,
from the blood we were talking about, I mean what's that coming
to say? So אמר רבא למעוטי שריים שבאצבע. amar Rava l'mutei shirayim
shebe'etzba.
What's left over on your finger. If you have to do more
than one sprinkling, like when you apply the application of the four
corners by a חטאת, chatas, or it's an inner חטאת chatas and
you do seven sprinklings towards the פרוכת, paroches, if you dip once
and you do one and you have leftover blood on your hand,
then you do two. Or do you need a separate act of
טבילה tevila for each application? And that's what we say, you need
a separate act for each application. It says וטבל הכהן מן הדם,
v'taval hakohen min hadam, so from the blood, means you're always taking
it from the original blood. מן הדם שבענין. Min hadam shebe'inyan. You're
never using the blood that was left on your hand, you're always
going back to that blood to do the sprinkling, the blood that
is collected in the vessel. So let's and let's take a look.
מסייע ליה לרבי אלעזר. Msayei lei Rabbi Elazar.
This supports Rabbi Elazar, דאמר, d'amar, who says, שריים שבאצבע פסולין. shirayim
shebe'etzba psulin.
The remnant blood on the finger is invalid, you cannot use it
for other sprinklings. אמר ליה רבין בר רב אדא לרבא. Amar lei
Ravin bar Rav Adda l'Rava. So Ravin bar Rav Adda said to
Rava, אמרי תלמידייך, amri talmideich, your students say, אמר רב עמרם, amar
Rav Amram, in the name of Rav Amram, another statement that sounds
like you can use the remainder of blood. What do they say?
תניא, Tanya, that we taught in the ברייתא. braisa. היה מזה ונזה
הזאה מידו. Hayah mazeh v'nitzeh ha'aza miyado.
So you might remember back to זבחים, Zevachim, one of the laws
is that if blood of a חטאת chatas sprinkles on clothes, they
need a special ritual of cleansing. And one of the things we
said is אשר יזה מדמה על הבגד, asher yizeh midama al habeged,
that it is sprinkled from and ולא אשר כבר הוזה, v'lo asher
kvar huzah,
not blood that has already been sprinkled. So the only time the
blood that goes on your clothes requires the special ritual of cleansing
is only for blood that has yet to be sprinkled. Okay, so
now given that, having that in mind, let's read this ברייתא. braisa.
Right, because you touched the side of the מזבח mizbe'ach already, and
then you're then you're okay. Right, it said אשר יזה מדמה ולא
אשר כבר הוזה. asher yizeh midama v'lo asher kvar huzah. So right.
So
then it says like this, so let's see what this ברייתא braisa
is. תניא, Tanya, היה
מזה, hayah mazeh, you were sprinkling, ונזה הזאה מידו, v'nitzeh ha'aza miyado,
and the sprinkling came off your hand or finger, אם עד שלא
הזה, im ad shelo hizah,
if the blood splattered from your finger to your clothes before you
did the sprinkling, טעון כיבוס, teun kibus, then your clothes need this
ritual cleansing. משהזה, Mishehizah, from
once after that you sprinkled with your finger, then the blood went
from your finger to your clothes, אין טעון כיבוס, ein teun kibus,
does not need a ritual cleansing. So what's the problem with that?
מאי לאו, Mai lav, are we not talking עד שלא גמר הזאתו?
ad shelo gamar haza'ato?
For some reason, it says that after the blood went off your
finger,
you no longer need it. They understand it does not mean they
understand you're doing a series of sprinklings, right? You're doing let's say
seven sprinklings, it's an inner חטאת, chatas, and he understands what it
means is not when you finish one, but when you're finished with
the entire process, then the blood that splatters is not a problem
because then it's כבר הוזה. kvar huzah. But somewhere in the middle
of the process, it would be a problem. And that would prove
that you can have a series of sprinklings with all one dipping
of the finger, okay, that you're doing it from the שריים shirayim
of the blood. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו, mai lav,
does this not mean עד שלא גמר הזאתו? ad shelo gamar haza'ato?
That as long as you're not done with your entire series and
the blood sprinkles, you need to cleanse the clothes. משיגמר הזאתו, mishegamar
haza'ato, when you're done with the entire series, ומשיגמר umishegamar
one minute, עד שלא גמר הזאתו ומשיגמר הזאתו, ad shelo gamar haza'ato
umishegamar haza'ato,
and contrasting it to when you're done with the series, then the
splattering of blood is not a problem. שמע מינה, Shema mina, and
from this we could infer דשריים שבאצבע כשרין. deshirayim shebe'etzba kesherin. If
we're talking about a series of sprinklings, all
with your finger multiple times, then we could say that the שריים
shirayim are מעכב. me'akev. Excuse me, then from that we can learn
that the שריים shirayim are still valid even on your finger. So
the גמרא Gemara says, לא! lo! No! Who says that's what it's
talking about? עד שלא יצא מידו הזאה טעון כיבוס ומישיצא מידו ונזה
ממה שנשאר אין טעון כיבוס. Ad shelo yaftza miyado ha'aza teun kibus
umisheyatza miyado v'nitzeh mima shenish'ar ein teun kibus. I mean,
where do you get off reading it that way to ask the
question? Before it left your finger the first time, then if it
splatters on you, you need כיבוס kibus on your clothes. After it
left... the first time then if it splatters on you, you need
כיבוס kibus on your clothes. After it left the first time it
splatters on you, you don't need כיבוס. kibus. But there's no indication
that we're talking about a series, we're talking about one dipping, before
you did the sprinkling and after you did the sprinkling. So for
whatever bizarre reason they had read that ברייתא braita to be referring
to a series and whether it splattered during the series or after
the series, but of course the ברייתא braita could just as easily
maybe even more פשט pshat be read, a single sprinkling, before after
you had done the sprinkling. So that's no evidence. Okay, so we
have this side issue about whether you can continue sprinkling or you
need to dip each time. Some of this is just the, you
know, practical details about how do you do the dipping? You have
to dip it into the pool of liquid, not go around the
edges. You have to do a separate dipping for each sprinkling. That's
not directly our issue. What is directly our issue is you have
to catch the minimum amount of blood in the vessel. And similarly
we're saying if you learn a מנחה mincha from דם, dam, which
רב Rav does, it's רב, Rav, right? Which רבא. Rava. No, רבא
Rava does, if you learn a מנחה mincha from דם, dam, then
you have to catch, then you have to place a minimum amount
of the מנחה mincha in a vessel. And again there are two
important themes here. One is that we're not just talking about the
עבודה avodah of קבלת הדם. kabalat hadam. The language being used here
is whether the כלי kli is מקדש. mekadesh. And it needs the
minimum amount to be מקדש. mekadesh. So it's actually about raising a
level of sanctity. The other important point is, you know, to note
that again this question about are we doing an עבודה avodah or
not, that there could have been a difference between the blood and
the מנחה, mincha, because the blood, the עבודה avodah is קבלה. kabala.
By the מנחה, mincha, the עבודה avodah is the placing. So therefore
there could have been exactly that difference, but the גמרא Gemara is
denying it, and part of that denial of the difference comes from
the focus on the קידוש kidush of the vessel and not on
the עבודה. avodah. If your emphasis is on the עבודה, avodah, then
you would have said oh that's an עבודה avodah of קבלה, kabala,
this is an עבודה avodah of נתינה, netina, and you don't need
to do the same thing. But if we're saying that the similarity
is how the vessel operates to effect קידוש, kidush, then we could
say you need a minimum amount of blood, you need a minimum
amount of מנחה. mincha. You need the vessel to be off the
ground, you need the vessel to be off the ground. So by
comparing the function of the vessel, we're making this equation. Okay, so
now let's continue.
Okay, אתיבי אביי. Eitivei Abaye. So אביי Abaye asked. Are we good
with that? We are done with the major point, we're going to
continue asking whether we learn מנחה mincha from blood or not in
other ways. Okay, אתיבי אביי, Eitivei Abaye, we are at the end
of the first wide line. גמר מלהזות מקנח ידו בגופה של פרה.
Gamar milhazot mekanuach yado begufah shel parah. So this is during the
processing of the פרה אדומה parah adumah before it's turned into ashes
yet. The כהן kohen slaughters the פרה parah and it says he
takes some of the blood and he sprinkles seven times out of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, sprinkles seven times towards the מקדש. Mikdash.
So when he is done sprinkling,
so we are still, excuse me, we're still trying to prove whether
you have to do a separate dipping each time. So it says
he's done with his sprinkling, then he wipes his finger on the
פרה אדומה parah adumah itself. Why are we trying to prove he
used separate dipping?
Because in a ברייתא braita we quoted in one of our digressions,
it said מן הדם שבאצבעו, min hadam shebe'etzba'o, which caught us, right,
it caught our digression to figure out do you have to dip
a separate time for each sprinkling. So it says when he finishes
sprinkling for the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, then he's what do you
call it, then then then he wipes his finger on the פרה
parah itself because one of the מצוות mitzvot is it says ושרף
את הפרה לעיניו ושרף את בשרה ואת דמה על פרשה ישרוף. vesaraf
et haparah le'einav vesaraf et besarah ve'et damah al pirsha yisrof. So
you have to burn the remnant of the blood. So what else
is he going to do with the remnant of the blood on
his fingers? He wipes it on the פרה. parah. But that's when
he's done with the sprinkling. So that's אביי's Abaye question. גמר אין,
Gamar in, when he's done yes, לא גמר לא, lo gamar lo,
when he's not done no, which sounds like he does seven straight
sprinklings from what's on his finger and he doesn't do a separate
dipping. So אמר ליה, amar leih, he said back to him no,
גמר, gamar, when you're done, מקנח ידו, mekanuach yado, then you wipe
it on the
פרה parah and your whole hand, because you've got you know blood
that's been dripping around. לא גמר, Lo gamar, when you're not done,
מקנח אצבעו. mekanuach etzba'o. You don't have to wipe off your whole
hand, you just have to clean off your finger if you need
to do a new dipping, right? You don't have to worry that
your hand is dirty, you just have to get your finger clean
so you can do a new dipping. The גמרא Gemara is assuming
that if you need to do a new dipping, then your finger
can't have any of the old blood on it. So okay, you
make it is true it says when you're done you clean off
your hand, doesn't mean you don't do anything in the interim seven
sprinklings, then you clean off your finger. So this a thing that
you clean off your hand on the פרה, parah, your finger on
the פרה. parah. That's what it was about to ask. So the
גמרא Gemara says בשלמא גמר מקנח ידו בגופה של פרה. Bishlama gamar
mekanuach yado begufah shel parah. I understand when you're done you want
to clean your whole hand on the פרה parah itself, דכתיב ושרף
את הפרה לעיניו, dechativ vesaraf et haparah le'einav, which תוספות Tosafot says
the proof really is from the end of the פסוק pasuk where
it says ואת דמה ישרוף. ve'et damah yisrof. So you have to
get all the blood burned, so you wipe your hand on the
פרה parah so it can get burned together, so it can get
burned, that's when you're done. Yes, this was before. Okay, so that
I understand. אלא לא גמר מקנח אצבעו, Ela lo gamar mekanuach etzba'o,
but if before you're done you have to clean off your finger
so you can do a new dipping, so במה מקנח, bemah mekanuach,
what are you going to clean it on? Now the question is
not like why don't you just use a handkerchief, because the problem
here is what are you going to clean it on if you're
going to have to burn it later? Okay, right? If you have
to burn the remnants of the blood, what are you going to
clean it on? So the answer is not your handkerchief. Now, why
can't the answer be the פרה? Parah? So רש"י Rashi has two
explanations. One is he thinks has one scenario where the כהן Kohen
is at the top of a mountain so he can see the
מקדש, Mikdash, but the פרה Parah is at the bottom of the
mountain. Why he assumes that not so clear. The other explanation רש"י
Rashi says is, you know, because the פרה Parah is like icky,
sticky, and all of that. So if you're trying to really not
just get the blood off your hand but to get your finger
clean, you don't want to be using the פרה. Parah. So what
are you going to see things later? I mean, no, later you
just want to get
the—yeah, but bringing more blood by putting your hand your hand on
the פרה Parah if it's icky and sticky and whatever. But later
you don't have an alternative because—oh, well that's true if you were
concerned about getting more blood. Anyway, מסתמא שייפה, mistanma sheifa, the cow's
a large animal. It's not going to be at a—it's not going
to be icky-sticky everywhere. Yeah,
but you know, I agree with Michael, why you can always just
go to a part of the cow which is not icky. But
okay, anyway for whatever reason we don't think that you can say
that it's on the פרה Parah itself. Can't we clean on the
שפת מזרק? sfat mizrak? That's what we're about to say. You see,
you so much remember this סוגיא sugiyah from when we learned it
like three months ago that you already have the answer in your
head. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says, בשפת מזרק, b'sfat
mizrak, there you go, at the edge of the כלי, kli, like
any person would do, you know, you clean your finger at the
rim of the vessel and that's what you do. ככתב, Kichtiv, like
it says, כפורי זהב, kipuray zahav, which is a word, you know,
for golden things—did I skip? Did you skip parentheses? I skipped the
parentheses. Okay. כפורי זהב, kipuray zahav, the gold vessels, and they're called
כפורים kipurim because כפור kipur means to cleanse. So therefore you can
use the vessel to cleanse your finger. Okay. So basically the upshot
is, doesn't it sound by the פרה אדומה—I Parah Adumah mean, we
normally imagine this, right, and when you think about what we talk
about by יום כפור, Yom Kippur, right, we normally think he goes
in, he dips his finger, אחת אחת ואחת אחת ושתים. achat achat
v'achat achat v'shtayim. We don't think that he's dipping in between. But
this is actually saying that according to this approach, you have to
dip in between. It asked from the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah where
it sounds like it was an uninterrupted series. And it says, no,
between each sprinkling, clean off your finger on the כלי kli and
dip again. Okay. So that was a total digression. Now, we are
back to the question about a מנחה mincha in one vessel or
two vessels. Can you put the קומץ kometz in—in one or two
vessels? And basically now we have said that since רבא Rava learns
it out from blood, everybody would say that you have to put
the קומץ kometz into one vessel. Let's take a look. ומי אמר
רבי אלעזר הכי? U'mi amar Rabbi Elazar hachi? Did רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar really say
that—now I have to remember רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, where was he
in this? Hold on.
Or mat—hold on.
Where was רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar in this?
כמה
שהוא. Kamah sheh-hu. אף על גב דלא קדיש בחצאין. Af al gav
d'lo keedish b'chatza'in. Oh, oh I'm sorry, right, right, right. Thank you.
So the first stage of all of this was by the blood
to say that the same way the קומץ—in kometz order to say
the קומץ kometz has to be in one vessel, you said that
the blood was in one vessel. And we learned the blood from
the sprinkling of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So ומי אמר רבי
אלעזר הכי? U'mi amar Rabbi Elazar hachi? Did רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
really say that by the blood it has to be in one
vessel and then—and once you say that then the מנחה mincha would
have to be in one vessel? דאתמר, De-itmar, it was taught, חביתי
כהן גדול. chavitey Kohen Gadol. Now, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol every
day would bring a מנחה, mincha, half in the morning and half
in the afternoon. And the other thing you have to know is
that this מנחה mincha was minimum size. The minimum size of a
מנחה mincha has to be flour that is an עשרון, issaron, whatever
the size of an עשרון issaron is, we can talk about that
later. So this מנחה mincha was minimum size and you split it,
half in the morning, half in the afternoon. Okay, so if you
think about what you're doing, meaning we won't talk about—we'll talk about
the קומץ kometz in a minute, but you're not having it at
a certain stage the entire מנחה mincha in one vessel. Okay, and
now the question is, how about before when you're making the מנחה?
mincha? Can you start by making it in two vessels, in two
halves, not having the full amount? We've been talking about the minimum
amount of the קומץ. kometz. Now we're talking about the minimum amount
of the מנחה mincha when you're—Meaning you never put all the flour
together? Yeah, you bring the original flour that you bring. You bring
half an עשרון issaron in this vessel, half in this, and you
mix separate oils and you mix them and you מקדש mekadesh this
half and this half separately. So you never put it in one
big one and then split it in two? That's the question. Do
they have to do that? Or do we say that the same
way you need a minimum amount of the קומץ kometz to be
sanctified, you need a minimum amount of the מנחה, mincha, which is
an עשרון? issaron? That's always the minimum amount. And again, notice the
only way we can compare this is because we're talking about the
functioning of the כלי. kli. If we were talking about the עבודה,
avodah, right, who cares what the עבודה avodah is by קבלה, kabbalah,
what that tells me about how I'm making the מנחה? mincha? But
we're talking about the way the כלי kli functions. All right, so
let's take a look. ומי אמר רבי אלעזר הכי? U'mi amar Rabbi
Elazar hachi? Did רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar really say that by דם
dam you need the minimum amount? דאתמר, De-itmar, it was taught, חביתי
כהן גדול. chavitey Kohen Gadol. When it comes to the חביתין, chavitim,
which is this daily מנחה mincha of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
רבי יוחנן אמר אינה קדושה לחצאין. Rabbi Yochanan amar enah kedushah l'chatza'in.
You cannot make the original מנחה mincha in two separate vessels, a
half of an עשרון, issaron, you cannot start off in two separate
ones. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, מתוך שקרבה לחצאין
*mitoch shekreva l'chatza'in*, since you're going to bring it in halves, קדושה
kedusha? לחצאין *kedusha l'chatza'in*, you can sanctify it in halves and you
can make half in one vessel, half in the other. Okay, so
now the question is, if we assume that everybody learns מנחה mincha
*mincha* from דם dam. *dam*, and if Rabbi Eliezer said that by
the דם *dam* you need to catch the minimum amount in one
vessel, how can he say that you can split into two vessels?
Now of course תוספות *Tosafot* says, what do you mean how can
he say? He said מפני שקרבה לחצאין *mipnei shekreva l'chatza'in*.
So maybe because there's a special exception here, מפני שקרבה לחצאין *mipnei
shekreva l'chatza'in*, which is sort of what Michael's saying. All right, so
תוספות *Tosafot* says, well why don't you say the same about the
blood? What do you do when you sprinkle the blood? If you
have to say seven sprinkles, you do seven acts of sprinkling. So
why don't we say מפני שנזרק שבע *mipnei shenizrak sheva*, so you
can be מקדש לשבע *mekadesh l'sheva*? Why do you need all seven
together? All right, so that's the question. So תוספות *Tosafot* bats at
that by saying that that's not what they meant at all to
begin with. But over here. All right, but anyway, I understand. But
it's a question, but let's bracket it and see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* answers. ואם איתא *V'im ita*, if Rabbi Eliezer says what
he does by blood, that you need the minimum amount, ליליף מדם
*leilyif midam*. דף ח עמוד א *Daf chet amud aleph*, first line.
וכי תימא *V'chi teima* Rabbi Eliezer מילתא ממילתא לא גמר *milta mimilta
lo gamar*. Ah, so remember, anyway to all these questions assume two
things: number one, we've established what it is by blood, and number
two, we can apply what we know by blood to the מנחה
mincha? *mincha*. So how, so we're asking why Rabbi Eliezer by the
מנחה mincha. *mincha* says you can sanctify it in halves, by blood
he says you need the minimum amount all together. So how do
those work? Well the, possibly the best way to resolve it is
to break the link, to say you don't learn out מנחה mincha
*mincha* from blood. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to
say, learn out. וכי תימא *V'chi teima* Rabbi Eliezer מילתא ממילתא לא
גמר *milta mimilta lo gamar*, he doesn't learn out one thing from
another thing. והאמר *V'ha'amar* Rabbi Eliezer מנחה mincha שקמצה בהיכל כשרה *mincha
shekamtza b'heichal keshera*, שכן מצינו בסידור בזיכין bazichin. *shekein matzinu b'sidur bazichin*,
בבזיכין *babazichin*.
So if you do the קמיצה kmitza, *kmitza* not in the עזרה
*azara*, right? And remember one of the, we learned that you can
do it anywhere in the עזרה *azara* because it says וקמץ משם
*v'kamat misham* ממקום שרגלי העזרה עומדות *mimakom sheraglei ha'azara omdot*. Okay, but
what if you do it in the היכל *heichal*, right, in the
inner sanctum where there's the שולחן *shulchan* and so on? So עזרה
*azara* is not allowed in the היכל *heichal*. So maybe it should
be invalid. So he says, no, the קמיצה kmitza *kmitza* is valid
even in the היכל *heichal*, as long as a כהן *Kohen* did
it, as long as a כהן *Kohen* did it, right. But why?
Because you do a קמיצה kmitza, *kmitza* in the היכל *heichal* anyway,
because when you take the בזיכין bazichin, *bazichin* from the לחם הפנים
Lechem haPanim *lechem hapanim* from the שולחן *shulchan*, that's a type of
a קמיצה kmitza, *kmitza*. So we see he's able to apply the
לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* to a מנחה mincha *mincha*. So why doesn't
he apply the blood to a מנחה mincha *mincha*? And of course
there's a very obvious answer. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מנחה
mincha ממנחה יליף *mincha mimincha yalif*, he's able to apply from one
type of a מנחה mincha *mincha*, the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*, to
another. מנחה mincha, מדם לא יליף *mincha midam lo yalif*, he's not
going to learn out the rituals of a מנחה mincha *mincha* to
blood. So what we actually have here is, you know, the, a
debate of the, Rava's initial question of can you do קבלה *kabala*
of the מנחה mincha. *mincha* in a כלי kli *kli* that's פגבי
קרקע *pagavei karka* becomes reframed as do we learn from דם *dam*
or not? And now we see that that's a general question going
on here. Rava learns from blood, so he says you have to
hold the vessel for the מנחה mincha *mincha*, that you have to
have the minimum amount all together. And also when you're making the
מנחה mincha *mincha*, you have to, even the חביתי כהן גדול Chavitei
Kohen Gadol, *chavitei Kohen Gadol*, you have to make it all together.
And Rabbi Eliezer says certain things you can allow, מנחה mincha ממנחה
*mincha mimincha*, but you're not going to learn מנחה mincha מדם *mincha
midam*. And therefore you can question all of these assertions because you
can't necessarily learn from what we know by דם *dam*. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on with this. ומנחה ממנחה
מי יליף *Umincha mimincha mi yalif*, is it really true that Rabbi
Eliezer learns from one מנחה mincha *mincha* to another? והתניא *V'hatanya*, we
taught in a ברייתא braisa *braita*: עד שלא פרקה נפרס לחמה הלחם
פסול pasul, ואין מקטיר עליה את הבזיכין *ad shelo pirkah nifras lachmah
halechem pasul v'ein maktir aleiha et habazichin*. So before you have removed
the bread from the שולחן *shulchan*, נפרס לחמה *nifras lachmah* the bread
broke. I'm sorry, עד שלא פרקה *ad shelo pirkah* means until you've
removed, yeah,
right, in which case that you have
basically the question is like this: you are removing, once again with
the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* and you're removing the בזיכין *bazichin*, but
then the, a piece of the bread breaks off. So the analogy
to a מנחה mincha *mincha* would be you've, one case scenario would
be a piece of the מנחה mincha. *mincha* got lost before you
did the קומץ kometz, *kometz*. Another scenario would be you did the
קומץ kometz, *kometz* but a piece of the מנחה mincha, *mincha* got
lost before you burned it up. So are either of those פסול
*pasul*? So the first case is definitely פסול *pasul*. If the מנחה
mincha, *mincha* was not whole when you did the קומץ kometz *kometz*,
it's invalid. What if it, you did the קומץ kometz *kometz*, it
was whole and then a piece broke off? That's we'll see is
questionable and debate. So now we're going to see what's the story
by the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*. So you're removing the little, you
know, things of incense which is like the קמיצה kmitza *kmitza*, but
a piece of the bread, like a piece of the מנחה mincha,
*mincha*, breaks off. When did it happen, before or after? So let's
take a look. There's so many I never see that as happening
in the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. It's like, you know, everything there's
right, you know, miracles, there were never any problems. I know, but
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know, when you deal with the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, it sometimes it actually does bring. It's like a
פסול עומר. I know, but it normally assumes natural things can happen.
Okay, so let's take a look. הקומץ. Hakometz. But you put it
back, right, or not? Like if a piece of bread falls, can
you just like stick it back
on? Yes, presumably, yes. I don't know about the bread, because then
it's not really a whole bread like a מנחה mincha that's בלול,
balul, maybe I don't know. Okay, so עד שלא פרקה נפרסה לחמה
הלחם פסול. ad shelo parka nifrasa lachma halechem pasul. So if before
you removed the little spoons of incense a piece of the bread
broke off, then it's invalid ואין מקטירין עליהם את הבזיכין, ve'ein maktirin
aleihem et habazichin, and you cannot burn up the בזיכין. משפרקה
נפרסה לחמה, misheparka nifrasa lachma, if after
you have, if after you've removed the little cups, the little spoons,
then bread broke off, משפרקה נפרסה לחמה הלחם פסול, misheparka nifrasa lachma
halechem pasul,
it is true that the bread is פסול, which means the כהנים
kohanim can't eat the bread. What do they do then? Burn it.
ומקטיר עליהם את הבזיכין. umaktir aleihem et habazichin.
You can still bring, the קרבן korban is כשר, kasher, as it
were, you can still bring the בזיכין, but because this accident happened
before the incense was burnt, the bread is invalid. Okay, so that's
interesting. How does that parallel or not parallel to a מנחה? mincha,
And first let's see what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says. אמר רבי
אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says, לא פרקה ממש
אלא כיון שהגיע זמנה לפרק. lo parka mamash ela keivan shehigia zmana
lefarek. It doesn't literally mean that you have undone it, meaning that
you've removed the spoons of incense, it just means it's the time
to remove them. לפרק אף על פי שלא פרקה כמי שפרקה דמי,
lefarek af al pi shelo parka kemi sheparka dami, even if you
have not removed it, it's like you removed it. So now we
are going to say that's our question, meaning say that you have
the first part, maybe that's exactly analogous to a מנחה. mincha, Maybe
if the מנחה mincha, was lacking before the קמיצה, kmitza the whole
thing is ruined. Maybe if you did the קמיצה and then a
part got lacking, you can't eat the שיריים, shirayim, but you can
burn the קומץ, kometz exactly analogous to the bread. That we can
accept. But the problem is we've never heard of this idea by
the מנחה mincha. that when the time comes to remove the קומץ,
kometz it's like the קומץ kometz has removed. So how can he
learn one from the other if this parallel does not exist? So
let's take a look. ואמאי, ve'amai, if רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar really
learns מנחה mincha. from מנחה mincha. and מנחה mincha, from the bread,
תהא כמנחה שחסרה קודם קמיצה. tehe kemincha shechasra kodem kmitza. Let's say
the bread will be like a מנחה mincha, that was lacking before
the קמיצה, and we don't say that since the time came to
do the קמיצה, it's not a problem. גמרא Gemara says, לא
קשיא, lo kashya, that's not difficult. מנחה לא בריר ברירה קומץ דידיה.
mincha lo barir breira kometz didey. The מנחה, mincha the קומץ kometz.
has not defined. You've got this whole thing, it's one big square,
you don't know where you're going to take the קומץ kometz from.
So therefore you can't say when the time comes, it's like the
קומץ kometz was already
taken. והא, veha, in the case of the bread and the incense,
בריר ברירה קומץ דידה. barir breira kometz dida. Its קומץ kometz is
defined, it's these little spoons of incense. וכיון שהגיע זמנה לפרק כמאן
דפרקה דמי, vekeivan shehigia zmana lefarek keman deparka dami, once the time
came to remove them, it's like you already removed them. Okay, so
then yeah, you can learn מנחה mincha from the bread, but sometimes
there will be physical realities that are different that's going to lead
to a different הלכה. halacha. So the reason by the bread
when the time has come it's like it's already taken is because
you know exactly what needs to be removed and it's not all
one unit that has yet to be divided. Okay, so now the
גמרא's Gemara just going to be sure that the comparison holds. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מעתה תהא כשיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה.
ela me'ata tehe keshirayim shechasru bein kmitza lehaktara. Okay, let's compare the
bread to a case of a מנחה. mincha What would be, not
שירים, shirim, שיריים, shirayim, what would be
if the remnant of the מנחה mincha a piece got lacking after
you did the קמיצה before you burned it? So we are going
to assume that this is the הלכה, halacha, דאין מקטירין קומץ דידה,
de'ein maktirin kometz didah, that in
that case you cannot offer up the קומץ. kometz. So how come
here if it got lacking after you took the incense עליהם, aleihem,
thank you, you don't bring the קומץ kometz on them? So why
don't we say the same thing here? So the גמרא Gemara says,
who says that's the הלכה? halacha? לאו פלוגתא היא, lav plugta hi,
isn't this a debate? רבי אלעזר סבר לה כמאן דאמר שיריים שחסרו
בין קמיצה להקטרה מקטיר קומץ עליהם. Rabbi Elazar savar lah keman de'amar
shirayim shechasru bein kmitza lehaktara maktir kometz aleihem. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
holds like the opinion that if שיריים shirayim the remnant of the
מנחה was lacking between the קמיצה and the הקטרה, haktara, then you
could burn the קומץ kometz on them. So therefore we have a
perfect analogy except where it's physically not similar.
So the
הלכה halacha again is, you before you take the קומץ the מנחה
is lacking, so then the whole קרבן korban has to be burned.
You can't take the קומץ. If you took the קומץ and then
the מנחה was lacking, the קומץ remains good, burn it on the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, but the מנחה can't be eaten. The מנחה has to
be burned. Similarly by the bread, if the bread was lacking before
you took the little things of the incense, then forget about it,
you can't even burn the incense. If you took the incense and
then something happened, burn the incense, still don't eat the bread, exact
comparison, only difference is that by the incense it's enough that it
הגיע זמנה, higia zmana, you don't need to actually take it, but
that's because it's physically distinct that way from the מנחה. I would
also end. I would also set another difference that the גמרא Gemara
did not say. The same way there's not a distinct part of
the קרבן korban by the מנחה, there's also not a distinct time
of הגיע זמנה, higia zemana, right? If it's my own מנחה, I
can bring it today, I can bring it tomorrow, there's no specific
time. By שבת Shabbos and the bread, there's a distinct time. This
שבת, Shabbos, after רש"י Rashi says that the הגיע זמנה higia zemana
רש"י Rashi says I think you put the new ones on the
side or something like that. Exactly. Something like that. So there is
a very specific time. Right. רש"י Rashi says afternoon, after שש שעות.
sheish sha'os. So there's a very specific time where you can say
הגיע זמנה. higia zemana. We're way at near the top, like about
10 lines down from the narrow line. Okay, so there I would
say is the other difference. But other than that, you learn one
from the other. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes back.
גופא. Gufa. Now we're going to look at this debate about the
חביתין. chavitin. חביתי כהן גדול, chavitei Kohen Gadol, רבי יוחנן אמר אינה
קדושה לחצאין, Rabbi Yochanan amar eina kedusha lachatzayin, רבי אלעזר אומר מתוך
שקרבה לחצאין קדושה לחצאין. Rabbi Elazar omer mitoch shekreva lachatzayin kedusha lachatzayin.
So we've already said רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is not constrained by
the case of blood. He does not learn out by blood. So
he can say that maybe you can sanctify in two halves, and
that's what he says. Something certainly like the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol
קרבן, korban, which is going to be brought in halves, can be
initially sanctified in halves, whereas רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, you
always have to sanctify the full amount. All right,
so let's see what we do with this debate. אמר רב אחא
מאי טעמא דרבי יוחנן? Amar Rav Achaf mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yochanan? אמר
קרא מנחה מחציתה בבוקר ומחציתה בין הערבים. Amar Kra: Mincha machatzitah baboker
u'machatzitah bein ha'arbayim. It says a מנחה, half in the morning, half
in the afternoon. ובין הערבים מחציתה בערב. Bein ha'arbayim machatzitah ba'erev. Right,
I'm sorry. הביא מנחה ואחר כך חצאו. Heivei mincha ve'achar kach chatzo'o.
So it says just read the פסוק. pasuk. It says you have
a מנחה and then it says מחציתה, machatzitah, half of it, which
means you start with the whole thing and then you take half
of the whole. So that's a good read of the פסוק. pasuk.
So the גמרא Gemara says: מתיבי חביתי כהן גדול לא היו באות
לחצאין. Meisivei: Chavitei Kohen Gadol lo hayu ba'ot lachatzayin.
Here we have a ברייתא braisa: that says this is a מתיבי
meisivei not on רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's a מתיבי meisivei on
רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Okay. You would not bring it in two
halves. לא היו באות לחצאין אלא מביא עישרון שלם וחוצהו. Lo haya
ba'ot lachatzayin ella meivi isaron shaleim vechotzehu. Take the full עישרון isaron
and then after you've made the מנחה, then you break it. ותניא,
Vetanya, we taught in a ברייתא: אילו נאמר מנחה מחצית, Illu ne'emar
mincha machatzit, half of a מנחה, הייתי אומר מביא חצי עישרון מביתו
שחרית ומקריב חצי עישרון מביתו ערבית ומקריב. hayiti omer meivi chatzi isaron
mibeito shacharit u'makriv, chatzi isaron mibeito arvit u'makriv. He brings half of
an עישרון isaron in the morning and makes it into a מנחה,
and half of an עישרון isaron in the afternoon and makes it
a מנחה. But the פסוק pasuk doesn't say that. It doesn't say
half a מנחה. תלמוד לומר מחציתה בבוקר. Talmud lomar machatzitah baboker. אי
מנחה, Ei mincha, half of it.
So you need to start with a whole מנחה. מחצה משלם הוא
מביא. Mechtza mishalem hu meivi. He brings a half of a whole.
So here we have very nice פסוקים pesukim and ברייתות braisas that
say like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. You have to bring the full
amount against רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is
one word: למצוה. Lemitzvah. All of that is לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Now, again,
other than just saying "Oh it's לכתחילה l'chatchila not בדיעבד" b'dieved and,
you know, a cheap answer or something like that, I really want
us to get into focus on the difference here about כלי שרת
klei shares versus עבודה. avodah. Okay? What the גמרא Gemara? should be
saying is, למצוה, lemitzvah, remember the phrasing used before was, you know,
whether a כלי שרת klei shares is מקדש לחצאין mekadeish lachatzayin and
whether it's קדוש kadosh or אינו קדוש. eino kadosh. So all רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is saying here is it's קדוש. kadosh. He's not
saying you're following what the פסוקים pesukim are saying. You're right. The
פסוקים pesukim are saying make a מנחה, divide it in half. I
have no debate with you. That's how the עבודה avodah should be
done. My question is, you didn't follow the פסוקים, pesukim, does it
still have the קדושה? kedusha. And can you still bring it even
though you didn't do... because we know by קרבנות korbanot you can
not do a lot of the rituals correctly and it can still
be okay. So fine, you didn't do this ritual correctly, but is
it קדוש kadosh or not? I will still say it's קדוש kadosh
because I will still say that a כלי kli can be, at
least by חביתין, chavitin, מקדש לחצאין. mekadeish lachatzayin. Yes, good question. מביתו?
mibeito? So this was done from his own personal funds? Yes. Okay,
it was the personal קרבן korban of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Okay. All right. So where did the גמרא Gemara say? Ah, so
וייטער. vaiter. So the גמרא says, ah, so
וחוקה כתיב בה. v'chaka ksiv bah. Doesn't it say
by the
כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol the חביתין chavitin a חוק? chok? And a חוק
chok means even by the rituals, right? Normally, I mean as we
said, this is the bizarre thing about קדשים Kodshim is that the
תורה Torah gives you a million הלכות, halachot, many more הלכות halachot
than by other places that are explicit. And nevertheless, maybe דווקא davka
because of that we say that you don't assume that they're מעכב,
me'akeiv, that without doing them it's invalid unless the תורה Torah repeats
it or says חוק. chok. So here what the גמרא is saying,
and the way I will read it is: Okay, you're saying it's
a ritual, it's not about קדושה. kedusha And that if it's just
a ritual, then if you didn't do it, it's still good. But
it says חוק chok by this ritual. So those are the rituals
that you have to do. Okay. So the גמרא says: וחוקה כתיב
בה, v'chaka ksiv bah, אמר ליה לא נצרכה אלא להביא שלם מביתו.
amar leih lo nitzrecha ela l'heivi shaleim mibeito. Okay, it says look,
there's two stages. One you bring the full amount, then you אמקדיש
*amakdish* it, you put it in the כלי שרת klei sharet *klei
shareit*. So somewhat ironically we're saying what is the תורה *Torah* saying
must? You're right. The idea of taking half of the מנחה *mincha*
that it has to start whole, it's as long as it started
at the initial point even before it became קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*. You
just came with your bag of flour, okay, but you come with
your bag of flour, it started whole. And now you can split
it into two vessels and be מקדיש makdish *makdish* it as separate,
right, which should be put in one vessel, right. You should be,
that's the קיום *kiyum* of a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. But again, that's
quite bizarre because again you would still think that to define it
as half of a מנחה *mincha*, it needs to be a מנחה
*mincha* together, not just a bag of flour. All right, so it's
a very strange answer. But again what I think is, you know,
significant here is the focus on the כלי kli *kli* as being
מקדש *mekadesh* as opposed to what is the exact עבודה avodah *avoda*
and the ritual. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this,
אמר ליה רב Rav גבי *Am lei Rav Gevi*... oh we just
did that. Okay, ומי אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan הכי *umi amar
Rabbi Yochanan hachi*, does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* really say
this, that it has to be all in one vessel? Now that
we're done attacking or questioning רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*. ואיתמר
*v'itmar*, it was said, הפריש חצי עשרון ודעתו להוסיף *hefrish chatzi isaron
ve'daato lehosif*. So let's say by any מנחה *mincha* you put a
half of an עשרון *isaron* into the vessel and you were planning
on going back and getting some more flour and putting another half
of an עשרון *isaron*. Can it be מקדיש makdish *makdish* a half
of an amount? Okay, so רב Rav אמר אינו קדוש kadosh *Rav
amar eino kadosh*, it cannot. רבי יוחנן אמר קדוש kadosh. *Rabbi Yochanan
amar kadosh*, it can sanctify. So here רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is
sanctifying half of an amount. How come he did not allow you
to sanctify half of the amount by the כהן *kohen*? So ואם
איתא לילף מחביתין leilaf meiHavitin? *ve'im ita leilef meichavittin*. Why not learn
from חביתין havitin, *chavittin*? If רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* feels you can
learn from blood to חביתין havitin, *chavittin*, you can certainly learn from
חביתין havitin, *chavittin* to other מנחות minchot *menachot*. And if the חביתין
havitin, *chavittin* has to be the full amount, even if it's going
to be half, then this should have to be the full amount.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says, וכי תימא רבי יוחנן מילתא מילתא לא
גמר יליף *v'chi teima Rabbi Yochanan milsa milsa lo gamar yalif*? And
if you say רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* doesn't learn one thing from
another? ואמר רבי יוחנן *Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan*, שלמים sheleimim ששחטן בהיכל כשרים
*shlamim sheshachtan beheichal k'sherim*. If you שחט *shacht* a שלמים *shlamim* in
the היכל *heichal*, not in the עזרה *azara*, but in the היכל
*heichal*, it's כשר *kasher*. דכתיב ושחטו פתח אהל מועד *dichtiv ushchato petach
ohel moed*. You should שחט *shacht* it by the opening of אהל
מועד *ohel moed*. שלא יהיה טפל חמור מן העיקר *shelo yehei tafel
chamur min ha'ikar*. So if the whole idea of the שלמים *shlamim*
is in the presence of אהל מועד *ohel moed*, so certainly I
can do it in the אהל מועד *ohel moed* itself. Now that,
by the way, I want to say to remind you of an
important point. Then there's the חטאת *chatas* thing because the גמרא *Gemara*
says this by a שלמים *shlamim*, it doesn't say it by the
other קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. And תוספות *Tosafot* says there's a good reason,
because the other קרבנות korbanot? *korbanot* are never said that the significance
of their location is their relationship to אהל מועד *ohel moed*. The
גמרא *Gemara* says by the other קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot* where they're שחט
*shachted* by the north of the מזבח *mizbeach*. So even if you're
in the hei... so if you're in the היכל *heichal* it's not
so clear it would be כשר *kasher*, because maybe that's not defined
as the north of the מזבח *mizbeach*. But שלמים *shlamim*, there's a
particular emphasis of relationship to the אהל מועד *ohel moed*. For example
the גמרא *Gemara* says if you שחט שלמים קודם שנפתחו דלתות ההיכל
פסולים *shacht shlamim kodem sheniftchu daltot haheichal psulin*. Before the doors of
the היכל *heichal* were opened they're פסול *pasul* because it's not פתח
אהל מועד *petach ohel moed*. What about other קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*? It
doesn't say, not so clear. Okay, so therefore the שלמים *shlamim* that
the whole point is relationship to אהל מועד *ohel moed*, if you
שחט *shacht* those in the היכל *heichal* they're כשר *kasher*. Okay, so
that's what רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says. That was a fascinating הלכה
halakha *halacha*. How is that relevant? It's relevant because the גמרא *Gemara*
assumes that that tells us that you infer one thing from another.
The same way פתח אהל מועד *petach ohel moed* is good, so
in אהל מועד *ohel moed* is good. So why don't we refer
חביתין havitin? *chavittin* to the מנחה *mincha*? Now that's a bizarre question
anyway, because here you're learning the same thing, the שלמים *shlamim* itself
if it's פתח *petach* can be inside. That doesn't mean you learn
from one type of קרבן *korban* to another. But be that as
it may, the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* would
agree you can make certain logical inferences. That really seems to be
the point. You know, the reason by קדשים *kodshim*, if you remember,
the גמרא *Gemara* had this whole י' *yud*... two דפים *dapim* about
whether when you can learn למה דמה למה דמה בקדשים *lama dema
lama dema b'kodshim*, like when you apply A to B, can you
apply B to C? And part of that is there are so
many rituals here at what stage do we say they are arbitrary
and you can't use logic, and at what stage do we say,
no, you can use logic. So that seems to be the point
of the גמרא *Gemara*. Since רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* uses logic to
say if it can be פתח אהל מועד *petach ohel moed* it
can be in אהל מועד *ohel moed*, why not use logic to
say if חביתין havitin *chavittin* has to be whole, then this has
to be whole? Okay, so we're back to that question. So let's
see the גמרא *Gemara's* answer. So the גמרא *Gemara* says exactly what
anybody would have thought and that Michael said, דעתו להוסיף da'ato lehosif,
שאני *daato lehosif shani*. No. The whole point is if you did
just a half it doesn't work. If you're planning on doing the
other half then you're part of a process and then it will
work. And that's different than the חביתין havitin. *chavittin* where you only
did half and wanted it to remain half. דתניא *D'tanya*, we taught
in the ברייתא *baraita*, מלאים melayim *malei'im*. This is by the קרבן
*korban* of the נשיאים *nesi'im*. It says that they brought these vessels
שניהם מלאים סולת בלולה בשמן למנחה *shneihem malei'im solet belula bashemen lemincha*,
סולת *solet* mixed with oil for a מנחה *mincha*. So what and
that's another proof that you that you learn מילתא ממילתא even from
something that is a very distinct הוראת שעה. hora'at sha'ah. So what
does מלאים mean? So literally it means full, but the גמרא's going
to understand that from there you learn that when you measure out
things they have to be a full amount. So let's see what
that means. אין מלאים אלא שלמים. ein melayim ela sheleimim. It only
is full. Now a lot we've been skipping, you might notice, a
lot of parentheses, because as I've told you before, there's a lot
of textual issues and there's a lot of glosses as well. And
here you can clearly see the nature of the gloss. We'll read
the parenthesis so you see that it's not just a textual issue,
it's a gloss. כלומר, klomar, right? When do you ever have כלומר
klomar in the גמרא? כלומר שאינו קדוש עד שיהא עשרון שלם. klomar
she'eino kadosh ad sheyehe isaron shaleim. Okay, clearly that is a gloss,
you know, it's a somebody saying, oh, I, you know, like a
marginal notation. Okay, so שלמים does not necessarily mean full, but it
does mean that you have to measure in complete units. So anything
less than a full unit, the כלי שרת klei sharet does not
work for. So again, the theme here is not the עבודה avodah
of the מנחה, the theme here has completely been how כלי שרת
klei sharet function. Okay, so one of the things now we're saying
is they only are מקדיש makdish something that is a full unit,
not a partial unit. ואמר רבי יוסי אימתי? ve'amar Rabbi Yosei ematai?
When is that true? בזמן שאין דעתו להוסיף. bizman she'ein da'ato lehosif.
If you're not planning on adding to the unit. So if you
have a half, it's not מקדיש makdish it. אבל בזמן שדעתו להוסיף
ראשון ראשון קדוש. aval bizman sheda'ato lehosif rishon rishon kadosh. Every bit
you add is קדוש. kadosh. Now that's also a חידוש chiddush because
you might have said that it'll be קדוש kadosh when you finish
your process. But he's actually saying no, as you're doing your process,
since in the end it's part of a process of filling it
up, every amount that you put in becomes קדוש. kadosh. Okay, so
what have we established? A lot of interesting things. We've established, number
one, maybe you learn from blood, but the reason you can learn
from blood which has so many different עבודות avodot is we're learning
is how the כלי kli. functions. So if you learn from blood
you learn you need a minimum amount to make the כלי kli
operate, you learn that you have to be holding onto the כלי.
kli The question about the חביתין, Chavitin maybe even when the חביתין,
Chavitin, even though they're brought separately, they have to be מקדיש together.
Okay, these are the types of things that we would learn from
blood, which is really what we're learning is how the כלי kli
functions. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar has an interesting position by חביתין, Chavitin
which is he's saying I agree that there's a מצוה mitzvah, to
do it that way, meaning that's how the עבודה avodah works, that
you bring it together and split it. But in terms of how
the כלי functions, at least by חביתין, Chavitin. not necessarily by other
קרבנות, korbanot I will say that it can מקדיש separately. Okay, and
now we are saying, so that is what we have said, and
we've also said that there's a question of the issue of דמינא
מילתא למילתא damina milta lemilta is really a question of how far
does logic go when trying to understand קרבנות? korbanot Right? Are these
details arbitrary or can we say there's a system here? Meaning it
might be arbitrary, but at least it's an arbitrary system, not that
each thing is random, and that if it's a system we can
apply what we see from one to the other, and obviously the
inclination is דמינא מילתא למילתא damina milta lemilta or else it would
be a very boring מסכת. masekhet. Okay. So now let's do a
little bit more, just with one or two more lines. Okay. ורב
בחביתין כמאן סבירא ליה? ve'Rav beHavitin kman sevirah lei? So רב Rav
who said, I keep on forgetting who's saying what here. רב Rav
is saying, oh, that if it's דעתו להוסיף, da'ato lehosif. it's not
קדוש. kadosh That a half is not קדוש kadosh even when it's
דעתו להוסיף. Who does he hold like by חביתין? אי כרבי אלעזר,
i k'Rabbi Elazar, if he holds like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that
says that the חביתין can be sanctified separately, לילף מחביתין? Learn from
חביתין. That if they can be sanctified separately, so when you're filling
a vessel half up it should also be sanctified. וכי תימא רב
מילתא ממילתא לא יליף? vechitema Rav milta mimilta lo yalaf? If you
want to say רב Rav does not learn from one area of
הלכה to the next in קרבנות, that's not true. והאמר רב מנחה
קדושה בלא שמן. veha'amar Rav mincha kedusha belo shemen. A מנחה can
be קדושה in the כלי שרת klei sharet. before you've added the
oil. שכן מצינו בלחם הפנים sheken matzinu beLechem haPanim because לחם הפנים
doesn't have oil and it's קדוש. kadosh So even though your מנחה
is going to be a mixture of flour and oil, when you
put the flour in the כלי without the oil it's already sanctified
because we have מנחות menachot. that are sanctified without oil. I know,
I know. So yeah... oh, that I don't know, that's a separate
question. בלא לבונה, belo levona, it can be sanctified without having put
the לבונה levona on yet. שכן מצינו במנחת נסכים sheken matzinu beMinchat
Nesachim because the מנחה you bring with קרבנות doesn't have the לבונה.
levona. בלא שמן ובלא לבונה, belo shemen uvelo levona, he's building up
to that. Even if it didn't have oil or the לבונה levona
on it, that it could be sanctified, שכן מצינו במנחת חוטא. sheken
matzinu beMinchat Chote. So because by the מנחה of a חוטא, chote,
right? לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה כי מנחת קנאת
היא מנחת זכרון היא. lo yasim aleha shemen velo yiten aleha levona
ki minchat kena'ot hi minchat zikaron hi. Even when it's like there
it's the way it's supposed to be done, here you're supposed to
have the other thing, but nevertheless, if it works there, it will
work here. And it can be קדוש kadosh even without all the
ingredients. So you see רב Rav learns this something from another. So
if רב Rav holds that חביתין could be קדוש in a half
measure, why doesn't he say other קרבנות could be קדוש in a
half measure? And don't tell me חביתין, that's the way it's done,
because the whole evidence right now here is that רב Rav doesn't
care that it's that's the way it's done. He's willing to apply
from one case to another. So the גמרא says על כרחך רב
כרבי יוחנן סבירא ליה. al korchacha Rav k'Rabbi Yochanan svira lei. רב
must hold like רבי יוחנן that רבי יוחנן says that חביתין has
to be whole and therefore רב says that also by other קרבנות
it has to be the full measure. Okay, so what we have
said now is a lot of very interesting points. I'll just try
to focus on the כלי שרת. klei sharet How do כלי שרת
klei sharet operate? We've had a couple questions. Do they operate on
the ground? That was debated and we said maybe it matters which
stage of the process. Do they operate the full amount? Basically, they
need the full amount. We learn it out from דם. However, maybe
not. חביתי כהן גדול, some say רבי אליעזר says you could be
a half measure and maybe we could apply that to other מנחות.
We're not exactly sure. But the dominant approach is that they need
to be the full amount, and then what we've also seen is
that they have to be a even a whole unit. They can't
be a half unit. Again, and the question about what is דעת
להוסיף. daat l'hosif. So you have all of these different questions which
are all questions about how the כלי שרת kli sharet functions and
again the nice thing to highlight that it's about the קדושת כלי
שרת kedushat klei sharet is the point about the חביתין. So רבי
אליעזר says I agree that there's a מצוה, the עבודה is you
bring it whole and you break it in half. But if you
didn't do that, there's still another I would still say that the
כלי שרת would still function to keep it קדוש and it could
still be brought. Okay, be continued tomorrow.